好的。
Yep.
嘿，大家能听到我说话吗？
Hey buddy, people hear what I'm saying.
很好，能听到。
You're good, good.
好的，我想像上周一样开始，
Awesome, I just want to get started with similar to last week
上周，我们问了一些 util 实验的问题，
where we asked you about, the util lab,
我想先问一下 syscall 实验的情况，
I just want to get started by asking a little bit about syscall lab,
因为那是周四到期的。
since that was due on Thursday.
所以如果有人在实验中发现什么特别有趣的东西
So if anybody just has like something particularly interesting, they found about the lab
或者发现一个难缠的 bug ，
or a nasty bug that they found
或者只是犯了一个愚蠢的错误，
or just a silly mistake they made,
关于 syscall 实验，任何你想分享的都可以。
anything you want to share about the syscall lab to be， [that'd be great.]
不知道什么原因，我删除了 fork 中需要通过 mask 复制的部分，
I somehow managed to delete the part from where from fork where you have to copy over the mask,
我让它工作，然后我修改了其他东西，然后我测试它，
so I had that working and then I change something else and then I tested it for.
你好像掉线了。
Your audio is like cutting out.
哦，抱歉，你能听到我说话吗？
Oh, it is sorry, you hear me.
我听到了。
I hear you.
好的。
Oh, okay.
我想是的。
Yeah I guess.
基本上我以某种方式删除了 mask 的复制，
So basically I deleted somehow the copy of the mask
然后我的 fork 就不能用了，
and then my my fork didn't work anymore,
所以我想，之前还是好的，现在怎么不能用了，
so then I was just like I did that, how does it not work,
我花了很多时间去找问题。
so spend a lot of time figuring out. What I did wrong.
我意识到我把那行删除了。
And I realized I just deleted that line from the.
有没有人听不到 Luca ，还是只有我这边。
Is anybody having trouble hearing Luca, is that on my end.
我想只是你那边。
I think its on your end.
是的，我这边是好的。
Yeah I'm fine.
那一定是我这边的问题。
This must be on my end.
抱歉，现在应该好了。
Sorry, maybe that'll work better now.
现在能听到我说话吗？好的。
Can you hear me now, okay great.
我还担心我这边。
I was worried that I was just talking.
不，好像是我这边的问题。
No, no, seems to be on my end.
好的。
Alright.
好的，还有人想分享关于 syscall 的任何事情吗？
Awesome, will anybody else have anything they'd like to share about you of syscall.
有什么特别有趣的，
Anything particularly interesting,
或者实验太难了，
or was the lab absolutely horrendous
你觉得我们应该把它从课程中删掉，再也不做了。
and you think we should cut it out of the class, never do it again.
我有一些东西，概括来说，事情的顺序很重要，
I have something, apparently the order of things matters which is a general statement,
我试着理解 syscall 函数内的代码，
so I tried to determine the mass computation inside the syscall function.
在理解之前，我需要先做 tracing 。
Before determining whether I actually needed to do the tracing.
所有系统调用都能正确跟踪，除了 trace call 。
And so all the syscall we're getting correctly traced except that trace call.
这件事让我心烦意乱，
And I was really getting disturbed by that,
直到 David 指出，
until I think it was David who pointed out,
你知道，应该在 trace 之后进行计算。
you know you should do the computation after [you should trace] just like that's fun.
好的，很高兴你能找到这一点。
Alright. I'm glad you were able to catch that.
是的，顺序确实很重要，
Yeah order does matter,
特别是对页表来说，你们会发现，顺序在那里也很重要，
especially for page tables, you'll find I think that order matters there as well
而且贯穿整个课程，注意事物的顺序很重要。
and generally throughout the class, paying attention to the order of things will be important.
最好不要覆盖页表中的内容。
It's good to not overwrite things in page table.
我也有一些东西，事实上我现在仍然对此感到困惑。
I also had something which I'm actually still confused about.
我在调试内核代码时用了很多 print 语句。
Well I had a lot of debugging print statements in the kernel code.
然后我把所有的位都设置好，运行 trace ，
I then ran that trace thing with all of the bits set,
基本上跟踪了所有的系统调用。
so basically tracing all the system calls.
我看到了内核中很多 print 语句的跟踪，然后。
And, I think I saw a lot of tracing for the print statements in the kernel, and then.
然后我假设我的 print 程序读取和写入控制台，
Because and then I assumed that my print my print apps were trying to read and write to the console,
确实会写入控制台，
but that do write to the console,
但我想知道是为什么。
but then I was wondering why are we.
我想，我困惑的是，为什么可以在内核中使用 printf 。
I guess, I'm just confused why we're able to use printf in the kernel.
我最近没有看过 printf 的代码，
Yeah I'm not I haven't looked at the printf code recently,
但是我想有一个 printf.c 文件，
but I think there's a file printf.c
你可以自己看一下。
you might be a look at if you want to.
嗯，这里发生了什么，
Um, here what was going on there,
我认为 printf 函数是在那里实现的。
so I think the printf function should be [implemented in there].
至少我们的版本是这样的，
At least our version of it,
我不知道，或许其他工作人员可能知道是怎么回事。
I don't know perhaps one of the what are some of the other core staff might know what's going on.
在跟踪的时候，内核中的 printf 不应该出现，
And the printf in the kernel shouldn't show up as your traces,
因为内核中的 printf 不做任何系统调用。
because printf in the kernel doesn't call any system calls.
是的，我也是这么想的，
Yeah that's what I thought,
也许 tracing 不是从那里来的。
maybe that maybe the tracing was not from that.
是的，我不认为它来自内核中的 printf 。
Yeah I don't think it is from your printf in the kernel.
好的。
Okay.
好的，除非还有人对 syscall 有别的评论，
OK, well unless anybody has any other burning comments about syscall,
我想我们可以开始今天的讲座了。
I think we can get started with lecture for today.
我将谈谈 C 语言转换为汇编语言的过程和处理器，
I'll be talking a little bit about the process of converting C to assembly and processors,
今天更多是一个实用的讲座，
and this is more of a practical lecture today
至少这是我们的目标。
or at least that's the aim,
我们的目标是让你们熟悉 RISC-V ，
so the goal here is to get you all familiarized with RISC-V,
熟悉它的处理器、汇编语言和调用约定。
the processor, the assembly language and calling conventions for RISC-V.
这是非常重要的，
And this will be important,
虽然对页表来说不是特别重要，
in not not super important for page table,
但是对于这周布置的的 traps 实验来说是这样的。
but certainly for the traps lab which is will be assigned later this week,
对于调试和实现都是必不可少的，
this will be essential for debugging and implementing things,
因为你将直接使用 trap frame 和堆栈之类的东西，
because you'll be working quite intimately with trap frame and stack and things like that,
所以这就是今天的目标。
so that's the that's kind of the goal for today.
我的第一个目标是，
And, my first aim was to,
这是对 6.004 课程的一点回顾，
this might be a little bit of review from 6.004
或者你学过的任何其他计算机体系结构课程。
or any other computer architecture theme classes that you may have taken in the past,
我只想简单回顾一下，
but I just want to go over briefly kind of see
C 语言是如何转换成汇编语言的，
the C language, how we get to assembly
还有一点处理器相关的知识。
and I'm maybe a little bit about processor.
当然，在这节课的整个过程中，
So, throughout, and then of course throughout this lecture,
如果你有任何问题，可以随时打断我并提问。
feel free to interrupt with any questions that you have.
你知道，在 C 程序中，一般都有 main 函数。
So, you know, we have our normal main functions in C.
它们会做一些事情，也许是打印一些东西，然后退出。
You know they do something, maybe they print something, then they exit.
这些看起来都很好，
And this all looks well and good,
但正如你们从 6.004 知道的，
but as any of you are aware from 6.004,
处理器实际上并不理解 C 语言，
processors don't actually understand the C language,
它们理解的是我们称为汇编的东西，
rather they understand what we call a assembly
或者更具体地说，它们理解的是汇编的二进制编码，
or more specifically they understand the binary encoding of assembly,
这里我在照片中圈出来的
and so this here I've circled a picture of
是 SiFive 板上真正的 RISC-V 处理器。
an actual RISC-V processor from a SiFive board,
而且当我们说处理器是 RISC-V 时，
and when we say a processor is RISC-V,
意思是它可以理解 RISC-V 指令集，
that means that it understands the RISC-V instruction set,
每个处理器都有关联的 ISA 或指令。
so every processor has an associated ISA or instruction.
那就是一套指令集。
And that's kind of the set of instructions,
对处理器来说是可以理解的，
that makes sense to that processor,
每条指令都有相关的二进制编码或操作码。
so every instruction has an associated binary encoding or an op code.
当处理器运行时，
And when a processor is running
会看到一种特殊的编码，然后知道该怎么做。
and it sees a particular encoding, it knows what to do.
所以，你知道这块板上的处理器理解 RISC-V 汇编，
And so, you know this processor on this board happens to understand the RISC-V assembly
汇编从 C 代码编译而来，
which is what C code is compiled to,
所以让 C 代码真正在处理器上运行的一般过程是，
so the general process of getting C code to actually run on your processor is,
编写 C 代码，然后编程成汇编语言，
we start with C, it gets compiled to assembly,
这之间还发生了一些链接之类的事情，
and there's some linking and things like that happened between this step
不过我们不是一门编译器课程，
but that's we are not a compiler class,
然后汇编语言会被翻译成二进制。
so and then the assembly will then be translated into binary,
这就是我们看到的 obj 或 .o 文件。
and so this is the object or .o files that you see.
如果你在运行 make qemu 之后注意过实验目录中的内容，
so if you've ever paid attention to what's inside of your lab directory after you run make qemu,
你会看到很多 .o 文件散落在各处，
you'll see a bunch of .o files lying around
这些就是处理器能够理解的目标文件。
and those are the actual object files that the processor understands.
你们也看到了 asm 文件，
And the asm files, you've also seen,
你还没有写过任何汇编代码，但是如果你回想 syscall ，
you haven't really written any, but if you recall from syscall,
usys.pl 文件被编译成 usys.S ，
usys.pl is compiled to a file called usys.S,
而 .S 文件就是汇编，
and so .S files are assembly language,
所以你肯定已经到了一些 RISC-V 汇编
and so you've seen you've certainly seen some RISC-V assembly
如果你学过 6.004 ，
and if you took 6.004,
我相信你也看到过很多汇编代码。
I believe you've also seen a good amount of assembly language.
一般来说，汇编看起来比 C 语言的结构化程度要低得多，
An assembly looks in general much less structured than C,
你会看到一行接一行的指令，
so you'll just see line after line after line of instructions,
你会看到一些简单的东西，比如 add mult 等。
you'll see simple things like add mult etc, and so on and so forth,
它也没有好的控制流，没有循环语句，
and this doesn't have no nice control flow, there's no loops,
有函数，但不是 C 语言那种函数，
there are functions but not in the sense that you might remember from C,
我们看到的是标签，而不是真正的函数定义。
we see labels as opposed to true function definitions.
汇编语言，是一种低级语言，
And the assembly, so it's a much lower language
还有很多其他语言可以编译成汇编语言，
and there are plenty of other languages that are also compiled to assembly,
比如，同样的过程也适用于 C++ 。
so, the same process holds true for things like C++.
嗯，你知道任何一种编译语言，
Um, you know any any language that's compiled
最终生成相同的汇编语言。
will go to the same assembly language at the base.
这就是运行的基本过程，
And, so that's kind of the basic process of
计算机真正理解我们编写的 C 代码，
getting our computer to actually understand the C code that we're writing,
但要注意，我们指的是 RISC-V 汇编。
but you'll notice that we've been referring to RISC-V assembly.
在整个课程中，处理器都是 RISC-V ，
Throughout the course and the processor is RISC-V
这很重要是因为有许多不同类型的汇编，
and that's because, it it's important because there's many different kinds of assembly,
你可能不会自己使用 RISC-V ，
so it's unlikely that you're using RISC-V yourself,
比如你不会在上面运行 Linux ，
like you're not going to be running Linux on it,
相反，大多数现代计算机在 x86 上运行，或者有时候看到的 x86-64 。
instead most modern computers will run on what's called x86 or you'll sometimes see is x86-64.
这是一个不同的 ISA ，不同的指令集，
And this is this is a different ISA, this is a different instruction set,
它看起来与 RISC-V 很像，
it looks pretty similar to RISC-V,
但这是你经常在个人电脑上看到的。
but this is what you see in kind of your personal computers often.
所以，如果你使用英特尔处理器，
So if you use an Intel
英特尔 CPU 实现了 x86 ，还有 AMD 。
so Intel CPU's implement x86 and I believe AMD also do.
这是两者之间相对重要的区别，
And [this is] relatively important distinction between the two,
它们并不像看起来那么类似，
they're not quite as similar as they may look at first
这归结于一个事实， RISC-V 是我们所说的 RISC ，
and that comes down to the fact that RISC-V is what we call as a RISC,
RISC-V 的 RISC 部分指的是精简指令集。
the RISC part of RISC-V refers to a reduced instruction set.
而 x86-64 是所谓的 CISC 或复杂指令集。
And x86-64 is what's called a CISC or complex instructions.
这里有几个关键的不同之处，
And there's a couple of key differences here,
其中之一就是 x86-64 中存在的指令数量，
one is just the number of instructions that are present in x86-64,
事实上，创建 RISC-V 的动机之一就是
in fact one of the big motivations for writing, for for making RISC-V was
我们实际上有多少指令。
how many instructions we actually have.
在英特尔手册里，有三本完整的书可供参考。
In the Intel kind of handbook, so for reference, there's three full books,
包括 ISA 和一些统计数据，
that encompass the ISA and some statistics,
新的指令仍然以每月三个指令的速度增加。
I think there's new instructions have been added at a rate of three instructions per month.
自从 x86-64 发布，它最早是在七十年代发布的，
Since x86-64 was added, it was first published in the seventies,
大概有 15000 多条指令在 x86-64 中。
so I believe there's like north of 15,000 instructions in x86-64.
而 RISC-V 则相反，
And RISC-V on the other hand,
RISC-V 的程序集可以包含在两个文档中。
the assembly for RISC-V can be nicely contained within two documents.
某种程度上，
And so, a kind of going off of that,
在这门课上，我们不需要你们记住 RISC-V 的每一条指令，
we don't expect you in this course to memorize every single RISC-V instruction,
但是如果你感兴趣，
but if you are interested
或者发现哪条指令自己不清楚，
or you ever find yourself confused by what a specific instruction is or does,
如果你访问课程网站，
if you go to the course website
我们可以在 references 菜单下看到，
and we look under the references tab,
在 RISC-V 下，我们提供了特权指令和非特权指令集的链接，
under RISC-V we give you the links to both the privileged and unprivileged instruction sets,
这个文档给出了很多关于 ISA 的信息，
so this is kind of the document that gives you a whole bunch of information about the ISA,
但是注意，这个有 240 页，这个有 135 页，
but you'll note that like this is 240 pages, and this is 135 pages,
所以它比 x86 指令集小得多，
so it's significantly significantly smaller than the x86 instruction set,
这是 RISC-V 的优点之一，
that's one of the nice things about, about RISC-V,
因此，在 RISC-V 中，我们的指令更少，
so we have in RISC-V we have fewer instructions
而且指令更简单。
and not only that, the instructions are simpler.
所以，我的意思是，
So, what I mean by that is that,
在 x86-64 中有许多指令，
there are many instructions in x86-64 by,
比如，有 add mul sub 等。
for example, that referring to something like add or mul sub.
在 x86-64 中，有很多指令不仅做一件事，
In x86-64 there's plenty of instructions, that do more than one thing,
它们会执行一些复杂的操作，然后给出结果，
so they perform some complicated set of operations and then gets you the result
而 RISC-V 则不同，指令的范围往往较小，
and that's not the case with RISC-V RISC-V instructions tend to be smaller in scope,
比 x86-64 用更小的周期来运行每条指令，
and so they take less cycles to run each instruction then maybe x86-64 is
这只是设计者选择的一种权衡。
and this is just a trade-off that the designers chose to chose to undertake.
没有什么规范的理由，
There's nothing or you know there's no canonical reason
为什么精简指令集比复杂指令集好，
why I reduced instruction set is better than you know a complex induction instruction set,
它们各有其用途，
they each have their own uses, and so on and so forth
与 x86 相比， RISC-V 还有一个很酷的地方，就是它是开源的，
and another cool thing about RISC-V as opposed to x86 is that, this is open source,
是市面上仅有的开源指令集之一，
so one of the only open source instruction sets on the market,
这意味着任何人都可以为 RISC-V 开发电路板，
so that means anybody can develop a board for RISC-V
它来自加州大学伯克利分校的一个研究项目，
and it came out of a research project from UC Berkeley
这就是 RISC-V 开始的地方，
and so that's kind of where was RISC-V started
从那时起，它得到了很多公司的支持，
and since then it's been picked up and supported by a number of companies,
你可以在网上找到这个列表，
you can find the list online,
确实有很多大公司对支持开放指令集感兴趣。
but yeah there's tons of big companies that are interested in supporting an open instruction set.
事实上，最近 SiFive 开了一场发布会，
And actually I think quite recently there was an announcement made by SiFive
他们是 RISC-V 处理器的首屈一指的电路板制造商，
who are sort of the premier board manufacturer for RISC-V processors,
他们将发布一款适用于个人电脑的电路板，
that they will be releasing a board for personal computers
该板将采用 RISC-V 处理器，为了在个人电脑上运行 Linux ，
that should extensively a RISC-V processor designed to run Linux for personal computers
我记得是在过去一两周开的发布会。
and I think that's been released in the last week or two, the announcement about it.
如果你很好奇，如果你发现自己，
So if you're if you're curious if your find yourself
你知道，我在完成 6.S081 之后，很想使用 RISC-V ，
you know absolutely I want to use RISC-V after I finish 6.S081,
希望到那时候有处理器可用，
hopefully by that time there will be a processor available
可以在自己的计算机上运行 Linux 。
that you can run Linux on your own computer.
但是即使在日常生活中，
But even in your day-to-day lives,
你也很可能使用了精简指令集，可能你没有意识到这一点，
you're most likely using reduced instruction set even if you don't realize it,
所以 ARM 指令集， A R M ，
so the ARM assembly, so that's A R M,
也是精简指令集。
this is also a reduced instruction set。
And ARM is implemented by Qualcomm, the the snapdragon series of processors.
所以，如果你有一部安卓手机，很可能运行的是精简指令集。
So if you have an android phone, you are most likely running a reduced instruction set.
即使你用的是 iOS ，我忘了叫什么，
And even if you're using ios, ios I think I forget what the name of it,
但是苹果也有一些版本的 ARM ，
but Apple has some has some version of ARM,
他们也在自己的处理器上实现了，
they also implement in their own processors
这些处理器运行在 iPad iPhone 和多数苹果的移动设备上，
that runs on ipads iphones and most mobile Apple devices,
所以精简指令集随处可见，
so reduced instruction sets are present all over the place,
如果你在现实世界中寻找 RISC-V ，
and if you're looking for a RISC-V in the real world,
你知道，在 QEMU 之外，
you know outside of your QEMU,
你可以在集成设备中找到它。
you'll be able to find that in like integrated devices.
所以它是存在的，虽然不想 x86-64 那样广泛，
So it is present, it's not as certainly not as ubiquitous as something like x86-64
但它是。
but it's um.
Yes I yes I think Apple is as Lucas just said I think Apple is moving Mac to ARM.
我相信情况也是如此，
I believe that's also the case,
去年确实有一股精简指令集的热潮。
there's been in last year's definitely been a push towards reduced instruction sets .
英特尔指令集为什么这么大？
Given given how big the Intel ISA has gotten.
英特尔指令集这么大的原因是，
And the reason why Intel ISA is so big is because
因为他们非常关心向后兼容性。
they're very concerned with backwards compatibility.
所以如果你写了。
So if you write.
一个现代英特尔处理器
A modern Intel processor can run the same instructions
也可以运行三十四年前编写的指令，
that Intel code from you know 30 40 years ago was was written,
他们不弃用任何指令，以保证向后兼容性，
it so they don't really deprecate any instructions so that they maintain backwards compatibility,
RISC-V 更现代，所以不需要考虑这个。
that RISC-V is more modern, so it's not a worry RISC-V is.
如果我们回到那些手册，
Also if we jump back to those manuals,
RISC-V 的独特之处是它的指令是分开的，
RISC-V is unique in that it's divided,
所有的 RISC-V 处理器都有基本整型指令集。
we have what's called the base integer instruction set which all RISC-V processors, um.
如果我们有。
If we have fifteen.
Gabriel 在聊天中问道，
Gabriel asks in the chat,
如果有 15000 条指令，几乎不可能有效地使用它们，
if we have 15,000 instructions, it nearly impossible to efficiently pipeline them,
那么为什么需要这么多。
why do we need so many.
就像我说的，需要这么多指令，是出于向后兼容的原因，
Like I was saying we need so many for backwards compatibility reasons,
这是由你自己决定的，你是否认为这是非常重要的。
it's up to you to decide you know whether you think that's super important.
但是我想很多指令被简单的指令所[]，
But many of those instructions I think a ton of them are also [] by simply instructions
这是它们特有的东西。
which are their own kind of special class of things.
我从没见过
You won't I I I've never seen
英特尔汇编代码能充分利用这 15000 条指令，
Intel assembly code that makes full uses full usage out of the 15,000 instructions,
这主要是出于向后兼容的需要，并且保持简单。
but mostly this comes from a from a need for backwards compatibility and simply.
就像我说的， RISC-V 有一个基本整型指令集，
But like I was saying the RISC-V has a what's called the base integer instruction set,
它包含所有正常的加法、乘法运算，
which contains all of the normal add multiply things,
然后处理器可以选择实现其他模块，
and then processors can choose to implement a number of other modules,
你可以在这边看到，
which you can see along the side here,
可能你在屏幕上看不清楚，
it's probably impossible to read on your screen,
举个例子，如果你希望处理器
but for example if you want a processor,
支持单精度浮点型标准扩展，
you know that supports standard extension for single precision floating point,
你就可以包含 F 模块。
then you can include the F module.
这使得 RISC-V 更容易支持向后兼容，
And this makes it easier for RISC-V to support backwards compatibility,
因为你可以指出包含和支持哪些模块，
because if, you can just say what set of modules do I include and support
而编译器可以选择。
and the compiler can choose.
然后，编译器告诉我它支持这些模块，
Then, compiler can say okay, you know this processor is telling me it supports these modules,
所以我可以用这些模块编译这段代码。
so I can only compile this code with these modules.
好的， Bibik 说，
Okay, Bibik says
似乎使用 x86 而不是 RISC-V 处理器的唯一优势是
it seems that the only advantage of using x86 instead of RISC-V processor
可以获得更好的性能，
is the kind of performance you can get,
然而，这种性能是以巨大的成本、复杂度和潜在的安全性为代价的，
however, that performance comes as a massive cost and complexity and potential security,
我的问题是为什么我们还在使用 x86 ，
my question is why are we still using x86,
而不是转向 RISC-V 。
instead of moving to something like RISC-V.
好的，一个宽泛的答案是，世界运行在 x86 之上，
Well, a big answer that the world is run on x86,
我也没有一个更好的答案。
for I I don't have a great answer for why.
RISC-V 是相当现代的，
RISC-V is pretty modern too.
世界几乎都运行在 x86 上，
So the world as a whole pretty much runs on x86,
如果突然把处理器转换为 RISC-V ，
so if you suddenly start converting your processors to RISC-V,
你会冒着失去对一些重要事情支持的风险。
you run the risk of, you know losing support for a bunch of important things,
另外，英特尔在他们的处理器中也做了一些有趣的事情，
also there are like Intel does do interesting things within their processors,
比如在安全方面，有 enclave ，
like security wise, there are enclaves on Intel processors
而且近年来他们一直在做一些事情，
and there's things that they've been doing in recent years
试图提供额外的安全性，
to try to try and give you extra added security
英特尔确实实现了一些指令，
and some of those instructions that Intel does implement
这些指令对某些特定的计算是非常有效的。
which are hyper specific can be really efficient for certain, computations.
所以他们有这么多指令，
And so they have so many instructions,
你知道，多数情况下，一种情况对应一条指令，
there's often you know, a perfect instruction for a situation
这可能比 RISC-V 更有效。
that may be more efficient than then what exists within RISC-V,
但一个更实际的答案是，
but a more practical answer is
RISC-V 相对较新，
at RISC-V is relatively new
还没有真正为个人电脑制造的处理器，
and we just don't know, nobody's really making processors for personal computers,
SiFive 的发布会是最近举办的，
I think the SiFive announcement is super recent,
他们可以说是第一批这样做的人。
and they're kind of the first people to be doing that.
所以在实践上，不能运行所有为英特尔设计的软件，
so on a practical level, that and the inability to run all the software design for Intel
这是我最好的答案。
is is my best answer.
我们现在讲一下汇编，
So we've been now chatting a little bit about assembly,
我想先看一些实际的汇编代码。
so I just wanted to take a look at some actual assembly code.
这是一段 C 代码，
So here is the C code for what's below,
有一个简单的函数，一个累加器，
so this is a simple function that has an accumulator,
我们从 0 循环到 n ，
we loop from zero to n
然后将 0 到 n 的所有数字加起来，
and we sum up all the numbers from from zero to n,
然后返回这个值。
and then return that value.
这是最简单的级别，最简单的汇编代码，
And at its simplest level, this is the easiest kind of assembly,
你可以编译这段程序，
you can get out of compiling that program,
如果你真的编写了 C 代码，并编译它，
if you actually go into your own computer and you write the C code and you try to compile it,
你可能会得到一些看起来完全不同的东西。
you will end up with something that likely looks quite different.
这是正确的，有不同的原因，
And that's true for a variety of reasons,
我们会看到其中一些原因，还有一些是特定编译器的，
we have a some of which we'll get to and some of which are compiler specific,
现代编译器进行了大量的优化，
so modern compilers make a large number of optimization ,
当使用编译器将 C 编译成汇编时，
With it when they compile your C to assembly,
所以你的汇编指令看起来可能会不同，
and so your assembly instructions may look different,
例如，当你在 gdb 中调试时，
for instance while you're debugging in gdb,
可能会遇到一些东西告诉你某个变量已经被优化，
you may come across something that tells you that it's some variable has been optimized out,
意思是编译器决定不需要该变量，
and that means that the compiler decided it didn't need that variable
因此，这个变量会从程序中消失。
and so that'll be gone effectively from the program,
这是很直接的，我们把 a0 中的值移动到 t0 ，
but yeah and it's at its most straightforward, we're moving value that's in a0 the t0,
我们把 a0 设置为 0 ，
we're setting a0 to zero
然后把 t0 中的内容加到 a0 上，
and then we are just adding what's in t0 to a0,
对循环中的每次迭代，直到 t0 变为 0 。
for every iteration of a loop until t0 reaches zero.
这就是这段代码的意思。
And that's all that's going on in this piece.
Amir, 你举手了。
Amir, your hands raised.
我想知道 .section .text .global 是做什么的。
I was wondering what .section .text .global do.
global 表示你可以从其他文件中包含这个，
A global means that you can include this from other files,
如果我们去看，看一下 defs.h 。
so if we actually hop into, let's see defs.h.
这是你后面会非常熟悉的文件，
This is the file that you're will, if you aren't already, you will become quite familiar with,
包含内核中可能使用的所有函数
this includes basically all of the functions within the kernel that you may want to be using
在这里，我们可以看到，
and within here you know we can see that,
在我的文件中，已经包含了这些函数的定义，
in my my file, I've included the definitions to these functions,
这样， .global 保证这些函数可以从其他地方调用，
and so that .global makes sure that, that these these functions can be called from other places
而 .text 表示这是代码。
and .text just says this is code.
如果你回想一下书中的图 3.4 ，
So if you recall from figure 3.4 in the book,
我们去看那本书，
so that's if we go to the book,
我们进入页表进程地址空间，
and we go into page tables process address space,
在这张图中，这和 text 是一样的，表示代码。
so in here in this diagram, that's the same thing is text, so just means code.
这回答了你的问题吗？
That answer your question?
谢谢。
Thanks.
如果我们想运行，嗯。
And so if we want to run, um.
我们有一些汇编代码，
Let's say we have some assembly,
如果你发现自己对内核代码感兴趣，
also if you ever find yourself interested in what the kernel looks like,
我们可以进入，编译后你可以查看 kernel/kernel.asm 文件。
we can go inside the, after you compile you can look in the file kernel/kernel.asm.
这是 xv6 内核的完整汇编代码，
And this is the full kind of assembly for the kernel of xv6,
左边的每个数字都是一个标签，
and each of these numbers on the left here is a label
告诉你这个指令在内存中的位置，
that tells you where in memory, this in this instruction will be
这是很有用的。
and that will come in quite handy.
所以，这就是实际的，
And so here is the here's the actual,
使用实际的汇编代码，你可以看到函数的标签以及声明，
use the actual assembly code and you can see the labels for the functions and whether declared,
这在我们调试代码时是非常有用的，
so this is this is, can be really really useful as we're debugging code
稍后我将展示这一点。
and hopefully I'll be able to show that in a second.
但是现在我们回到第一个函数 sum_to ，
But for now we'll jump back to this first function, sum_to
我们看看如何在 gdb 中调试，
and we'll just see how we can examine that inside of gdb,
第一步，这里我有两个窗口，
so the first step is I have my two windows here.
.asm 和 .S 文件有什么不同？
What's the difference between .asm .S files?
嗯，我也不是很确定，
Um, not a hundred percent certain,
它们都是汇编，
they're both assembly,
我想 .asm 文件包含了许多 .S 文件没有包含的额外注释，
I think the .asm file includes a bunch of extra annotations that aren't included in .S,
通常情况下，你把 C 代码编译成 .S 时，
so usually when you compile your c code to .S,
你会得到一些不包含行号的汇编代码，
you'll end up with something that doesn't include all those line numbers and things like that.
如果你想知道如何获得 .asm 文件，
So, if you're curious about how we get asm file,
我想 makefile 会告诉你获得它的准确步骤。
I think the makefile will tell you the exact steps used to get that.
我们回到终端，我们有两个窗口，
And so if we're in our terminal, we have our two two windows,
首先要做的当然是启动并运行 QEMU 。
so the first thing to do is of course get QEMU up and running.
在 gdb 模式下启动，
So gdb, started within gdb mode,
现在我们卡在这里，然后我们启动 gdb 。
so now we're frozen here and then we can start gdb,
就像 Frans 教授上周展示的那样。
and what what what what professor Frans showed last week.
我想有些人会很兴奋，
Which I think some people were excited,
输入 tui enable ，会出现一个窗口，
you typed UI, enable you get this nice window
现在是空的，但在你调试时会很有用，
which is empty for now but will come in quite useful as you're debugging,
我们可以设置一个断点，
so we can set a break point
应该注意到这些代码都在内核中，没有一个在用户空间，
and I should note that all this code is living inside the kernel, none of this is in user space,
所以我们设置断点时没有什么烦人的问题，
so we don't have any of those annoying problems setting break points,
我可以在函数 sum_to 设置一个断点，然后继续运行。
so I can set a break point in the function sum_to and then just continue running.
现在运行该函数，你在 tui 中看到的第一个窗口是源码窗口，
Run that function and now, so the first window that you see in tui is the source window.
是的，像 David 说的， kernel.asm 左边的数字是非常有用的，
Yes, as David is saying those those numbers on the left of kernel .asm are really useful
当你调试的时候，你得到一个地址，它会告诉你，
when you're debugging things and you get an address it'll tell you,
所以你可以看到，
so you can see now,
我们可以在 gdb 中看到 PC ，即程序计数器，
even here we can see that the programs of PC here in gdb, is the program counter,
我们可以看这个地址，以 800 开头的，
so we can see this address eight zero zero so on and so forth.
如果我们查看 kernel.asm ，并查找那个地址，
If we go into kernel.asm and we search for that specific address,
我们可以看到它在，
we can see that it's the,
嗯，它出现了两次，因为函数调用，
um, it comes up twice because the function call,
我们看这里，这就是那个地址，它是 sum_to 的开头。
but if we look here, this is that address, it's the top of the sum_to function.
所以如果你在任何时候看到这些东西，
So if you see any time you see one of these,
所有内核地址都是 0x8000 这样的数字。
um all the kernel addresses will look something like a 0x8000 some numbers.
这些地址你可以直接跳转到 kernel.asm ，
Those addresses you can jump straight into kernel.asm
并找到发生问题的那一行，
and find the exact line of assembly where the problem is occurring,
然后可以在相应地设置断点，
and then you can set your break points accordingly,
现在 tui 的顶部窗口是源码窗口，
but for now, the top window in tui is source,
如果我们想要查看汇编，可以在 gdb 中输入 layout asm ，
and if we want to look at specifically the assembly we can do layout in gdb asm,
这会给我们所有的汇编指令，
and that'll give us all of the assembly instructions and ,
如果我们输入 layout reg 还可以查看寄存器，
we can also look at the registers if we type layout reg,
我们得到汇编和寄存器，
we'll get assembly and registers
如果你要浏览什么东西，
and if you find yourself what to scroll through things,
现在我们有三个窗口，需要指定聚焦在哪个窗口，
now that we have three windows, we need to specify which one is focused,
如果我想查看所有的寄存器，输入 focus reg 。
so if I want to look for all the registers, I'm going to focus reg.
现在我聚焦在了寄存器窗口，
And now my focus is on the register window
这时移动箭头键或者滚动，就可以在那个窗口滚动了。
so I move the arrow keys or scroll you'll start scrolling that window.
现在，我们聚焦在汇编窗口。
Now we can focus on the assembly window.
我们到了这里，就可以看到所有的东西，
And once we're here, we can see all of the things,
让我们看看，我们可以在寄存器窗口中看到，
so let's see, we can see in the registry register window,
我们可以看到 t0 包含这个值，
we can see that t0 contains this value,
可以看到 a0 包含这个值。
we can see that a0 contains this value.
当我们单步执行汇编时，可以看到，
And as we step through the assembly, we can watch,
t0 刚刚得到了 a0 的值，也就是 5 ，
say OK, t0 just got the value of a0 which was five,
它也高亮显示了发生改变的寄存器。
and it's nicely highlighted the register that's changed.
这里我们可以，如果按下 enter 键，会得到最近执行的命令，
Here and we can just, keep remember if we push enter we get the most recently executed instructions,
我们继续，将 a0 设置为 0 ，
so we can go through, we set a0 to zero
现在我们可以看到这个循环和其中一些值，
and now we can just kind of watch ourselves go through this loop and some of the values,
这就像是一个完整的[]函数。
and then this is like a complete you know [] function.
我们继续，
Then continue and live our lives
如果你想知道设置了什么断点，
and if you're ever curious about what kind of break points you've set
或者忘记了你在做什么，
or you lose track of what you were doing,
输入 info break 或 breakpoints ，
if you type info break or breakpoints,
就可以看到代码中设置的所有断点，
you can see all of the break points that you set in your code,
你甚至可以看到，这个断点已经命中了一次，
and you can even see okay, this break point has already been hit one time
这样你就能得到很多有用的信息。
and you get lots of useful information doing that.
如果你不想使用寄存器窗口，但需要查看寄存器，
If you don't want to have the register window, but you do want to look at the registers,
输入 info reg 或 info registers 或 i registers
info reg or info registers or i registers
任何一个都可以调出寄存器窗口。
or any of the numerous gdb shortenings will bring up the register window .
那么，有关于 gdb 的问题吗？
So with that is there any are there any questions about gdb?
简单的问题，我知道已经有很多关于它的[]了，
Simple ones, I know it's been, there's been lots of post some [] about it,
所以现在可以问一些简单的问题。
so now's a good time to just ask some straightforward,
我会展示更多 gdb 的用法。
well I'll be showing more usage as gdb.
你使用什么命令打开多个窗口？
What command did you use to open the multiple windows?
我使用的是 tmux ，
So I use tmux,
我可以从头开始演示，
so I can show just from scratch,
在这里，我打开一个新的终端，只有一个空白的终端。
if we go here, I open a new terminal, so here's just a blank terminal.
如果你输入 tmux ，在 Athena 上也是可用的。
If you type tmux and this is available on Athena.
嗯，我一会再回答下一个问题，
Um, I'll answer the next question in a second,
现在我在 tmux ，你可以从底部的绿色状态栏看出来，
so now I'm in tmux, which you can tell by this green bar at the bottom
在 tmux 中，有几种方式可以创建多个窗口，
and if you want to get so there's a couple ways you can do multiple windows in tmux,
你可以输入 control-b c ，
if you're, so you can type control-b c
如果你习惯使用 emacs ，对此会很熟悉，
and I know that sometimes if you're used to using emacs that will make a lot of sense,
但是对于不使用 emacs 的人，
but normal people who don't use emacs
就是先按下 control 键，然后按下 b ，然后单独按下 c ，
that's hitting control and then b and then hitting c on its own afterwords,
这会打开第二个窗口，
that will get you a second window
然后，你可以使用 control-b p 或
which you can then navigate between with control b and then p,
control-b n 在它们之间切换，
control b and n to go previous and next.
是的， David 刚刚贴出了 tmux 的 cheatsheet ，这很有用，
Yeah and David just posted that tmux cheatsheet which is useful
如果你想拆分窗口，
and if you want to split the windows,
使用 control-b % 会垂直拆分窗口，
I think it's control b and then the percent sign will split them, um, vertically,
使用 control-b " 会水平拆分窗口，
and then sign a double control b and double quote will split them horizontally,
这就是我如何得到它们的。
and so that's how we get them.
如果我们处于这种状态，可以使用 control-b o 在窗口之间切换。
If we're in this state, we can use control b and o to jump between our windows,
这就是我有多个窗口的方法。
so that's that's how I got multiple windows.
是的，[]。
Yeah [].
Ahmed 问，为什么显示汇编地址，而不是 C 行号。
And then Ahmed asked why is displaying assembly addresses again instead of C line numbers.
因为函数。
So because the function.
如果我们回到汇编函数，
So if we go back to the assembly function,
这完全是由汇编语言实现的，而不是用 C ，
this is implemented entirely in assembly and not at all in C
所以没有与此相关的 C 行号。
and so there just aren't any associated C line numbers for this.
如果我们要设置断点，
If we were to set a break point,
如果你输入 delete ，可以删除所有断点，
so if you type delete you will delete all your break points,
我删除旧断点，现在在 demo_1 中设置一个断点，
so I cleared the old one if I now set a break point in demo one,
这是一个 C 断点，然后继续运行，
so that's a C break point and continue and run this,
现在，我输入 layout split ，会得到 C 和汇编窗口。
now if I go here and type layout split I'll get the C and the assembly.
如果我只想要 C 源码窗口，可以使用 layout source ，然后就只有 C 。
Um, or if I just want to C source, I can do layout source and I'll just get to C.
这就是正在发生的事，
So that's that's what's going on,
基于这个事实，
it's just a quirk of the fact
它没有关联的 C 代码，所以看不到 C 行号。
that this doesn't have associated C code and so we don't see C line numbers.
关于 gdb tmux ，还有别的问题吗？
Any other any other questions about gdb tmux, and that sort of thing.
所以 layout split 用来
So layout split is the one that you use to
bring up this extra window of the source and assembling so on right.
是的，如果你使用 layout split ，可以得到源码和汇编窗口，
Yes yes, so layout if you do layout split that'll get you source and assembly,
使用 layout source 只得到源码窗口，
layout source will get you just source,
使用 layout asm 则只有汇编窗口。
asm will get you just assembly.
寄存器是单独的，你可以输入 layout reg ，
And the registers are their own thing where you type layout, reg I think.
是的，这会调出寄存器，
Yeah, that will bring up the registers,
但是，我不知道有什么方法
but unfortunately I don't know of a way
可以同时调出寄存器、汇编和 C 源码。
to get to register the assembly and the C code all at the same time
除了在 layout split 状态下使用 info reg 。
outside of using info reg with layout split.
我有一个问题，当我们在行中设置断点。
I have a question, so when we set the back breakpoint at line right.
嗯，
Um,
这种情况下，断点添加到类似 0x80006354 这样的地址，
it displays the address of the like in this case breakpoint to add to 0x80006354,
指令可能有多个， C 中的代码行可能有多个指令，
what any instruction might have multiple , any line of code in C might have multiple instructions,
那么显示的是哪一个？
so which one does show.
我想显示的是第一个。
I think it shows the first one.
对启动 tui 有问题的人，
And it's tu-, for the person who asked to start tui,
我想命令应该是 tui enable 而不是 enable tui ，不好意思。
it's I think it's tui enable, not enabled tui, sorry.
我想是的。
And I think yeah.
是的。
Yeah.
是的，再提一下，这里有一些 gdb 和 tmux 的 cheatsheet ，
Yeah again there's a hundred cheatsheets out here for gdb and for tmux,
如果你发现自己不会用，可以看一下。
as well so if you ever find yourself lost.
gdb 还有自己的内置手册，叫做 apropos ，
I t-, gdb even has its own inbuilt it's own thing called apropos ,
如果你输入 apropos tui ，
so if you look for apropos tui,
它会显示所有相关的 tui 命令。
it'll actually show you all of the commands that involve tui.
是的，这可能非常有用，但也有点令人不知所措。
So yeah, this can be quite useful, but it can also be a little bit overwhelming .
如果你使用 apropos -v ，它会给你提供更多信息。
If you do apropos -v that it will give you even more information I think.
嗯，我不记得了，我不经常使用它。
Um I don't remember, I I don't use it often myself.
但是如果你要查找或忘记了 gdb 中输入命令的确切方式，
But if you do find or if you forget the exact way to type the command in gdb
而且你不想使用谷歌，
and you don't feel like google
apropos 能够找到你要找的东西，
and apropos's will will often be able to find exactly what you're looking for,
还包括很多关联的东西。
in addition to a whole bunch of stuff you are looking for.
是的，所以这是非常有用的， gdb 也有很好的文档。
Yeah, so this is actually quite useful, gdb is extremely well documented as well,
所以，如果发现自己不会使用，你知道的，谷歌是你的朋友。
so um, yeah, if you ever find yourself lost, you know, google is your friend.
现在我们来看汇编和 RISC-V 以及相关的东西，
So now that we've kind of been over assembly and and RISC-V and these sort of things,
我想深入讲解一下细节，
I want to dive a little bit more into the specifics
你们在随后的实验中会用到，
of what you you really need to know for the lab coming up
另外，这也是对文档的一个回顾，
and also it'll be a little bit of review from the document
当然，我想勤奋的同学已经读过一遍了。
that you've of course, diligent students read through thoroughly in preparation for this lecture.
是的，这张表你们很熟悉，
Um, so yeah, this table will of course be a wildly familiar to you all
从 6.004 或你们自己读的资料中，
and from from both 6.004 and from what you've read,
这是寄存器表，
and this is the table of registers
寄存器是 CPU 上处理器周围预设的很小的位置，
and registers are little locations on the CPU around the processor predefined
它可以存储值，这很重要，
that it can use to store values and this is important,
因为汇编操作，如果你记得汇编代码，
because assembly operations if we remember from the assembly code,
汇编不是在内存上操作，而是在寄存器上操作，
the assembly doesn't operate on memory, it operates on register,
所以我们做加法、减法时，是在寄存器上操作。
so when we do add when we do subtract we're operating on registers .
所以你经常看到一种编写汇编的模式，
And so what you often see as the pattern for writing assembly
有一个 load ，将一些值加载到寄存器中。
is will have some kind of a load, so we'll load some value to a register.
这个值可以来自内存，也可以来自另一个寄存器。
And that value can be from memory, or it can be from another register.
这里泛指加载，而不是 load 指令。
And, and here referring to load in general, not the load instruction .
然后我们会操作，在寄存器上执行一些操作，
And then we'll operate, so we'll perform some operation on the register,
如果我们关心返回地址之外的操作结果，
and then if we care about the result of that operation outside the return address,
我们可以把寄存器的值存储到某个地方，
we will, we'll store that register to somewhere, to some locate,
将寄存器的值存储到内存中某个位置或另一个寄存器。
they will store that register to some location in memory or to another register
这就是通常的操作过程，
and that's generally the way things work
寄存器是执行任何计算或访问任何值的最快方式，
and registers are the absolute fastest way to perform any sort of calculation or to access any value
这就是为什么使用它们很重要，
and that's why it's important to use them
也是我们更应该使用寄存器而不是内存的原因，
and also why we prefer using registers overusing memory,
如果你们记得文档中，我们调用函数时，
so if you remember from the reading when we call functions
可以看到，寄存器从 a0 到 a7 。
so you can see here that registers a0 to seven.
一般来说，当我们谈到寄存器时，会使用它们的 ABI 名称来指代它们，
And in general when we speak about registers we we will be referring to them by their ABI name ,
不仅减少了混淆，也是一个标准，
not only is it less confusing, it's just a standard
也是你编写汇编代码的方式，
and it's also the way that you'll write assembly code,
这个，这些实际的数字并不是特别重要，
this, you know, these these actual numbers are not super important,
唯一有意义的情况是对于 RISC-V 指令的压缩版本，
the only case where it does matter is for the compressed version of RISC-V instructions
如果你想了解更多，可以查看文档，
and if you want to know more about that, feel free to read up about it,
基本思想是 RISC-V ，普通指令是 64 位，
the basic idea is that RISC-V, normal instructions are 64 bits,
但是也有一个压缩版本，指令是 16 位，
but there's also a compressed version, which instructions are sixteen bits
我们使用的寄存器更少，这种情况下，使用的寄存器是 8 到 15 ，
and we use less registers and the registers we use in that case are eight through fifteen,
这些是我们可以使用的寄存器。
those are the registers that are available to us.
有人提问，为什么这个 s1 寄存器 x9 ，
So I think somebody had a question about why is this s1 register x9,
为什么它与其他所有寄存器分开？
why is it, separated from all of the other's registers?
我猜是这样，
And my guess is that that's why ,
我们把它与其他分开，因为它在压缩指令模式下是可用的，
that we separated from all the other ones because it's available in compressed instruction mode,
而 s2 到 s11 不是。
whereas s2 to eleven or not.
这是我的想法，它是一个压缩指令寄存器，
And so that's the idea, that's that's a compress,
但是在寄存器之外，将通过它们的 ABI 名称来引用，
but outside of that register will be referred to by their ABI name
a0 到 a7 用于函数变量，
and so a0 to a7 are used for function arguments,
但是如果有一个函数接受的参数数量，
but if we have a function that takes
超过可以访问的寄存器数 8 个，
more than the eight arguments that those registers give us access to,
我们就需要内存，
we do need to use memory
但这在某种程度上也说明了一个事实，
but that's , this is kind of an illustration of the fact
当我们可以使用寄存器时，就不使用内存。
that we don't want to use memory when we can use registers.
我们只在必须的时候使用内存。
We only we only use a memory, we have to.
这一栏， saver 栏，
And this, this column here, the saver column,
也是非常重要的，
this is also extremely important
在我们讨论调用者（caller）和被调用者（callee）保存寄存器时，
when we're discussing registers caller versus callee saved.
这两个属于我也经常混淆，
And the terms are I confuse them regularly,
caller 和 callee 只有一个字母的区别，
caller and callee, the only differ by one letter,
记住它们最简单的方法是，
the easiest way that I've found to remember them is
调用者保存寄存器在函数调用期间不会保留，
that caller saved registers are not preserved, across a function call,
而被调用者保存寄存器会保留。
so and callee saved registers are preserved.
我的意思是，
What I mean by this, is that,
调用者保存寄存器可以被函数重写，
a caller saved register can be overwritten by the function,
比如我有函数 a 调用函数 b ，
so let's say I have function a which calls function b,
函数 a 使用的任何寄存器都是调用者保存的。
any registers being used by function a that are caller saved.
调用函数 b 可以在其被调用时覆盖，
Call function b can overwrite when it gets called,
我想返回地址（Return address）就是一个很好的例子。
and I think a good illustration of this is the return address.
你可以看到返回地址是调用者保存的。
Because you know you can see that the return addresses caller saved.
这一点很重要，因为每个函数都需要使用返回地址，
And that's important because every function needs to use the return address,
因此，当 a 调用 b 时，能够覆盖返回地址中的值是很重要的，
so when a calls b it's important that be be able to overwrite the value in the return address,
这就是为什么它是调用者保存的。
hence why its caller saved.
而被调用者保存寄存器只是我们使用的约定，
And callee saved registers are just are convention that we use,
所以，帧指针（frame pointer, s0/fp）非常重要。
the frame pointer is important for that reason.
这些寄存器在函数调用之间保留，
And those are preserved across function calls,
所以对于调用者保存寄存器，
so basically any register that is caller saved,
进行调用的函数需要考虑这些寄存器，
the function that is making the call needs to worry about those registers,
如果是被调用者保存的，
and if they're callee saved,
则被调用的函数需要考虑如何保存这些寄存器的值。
the function that is being called needs to worry about preserving the value in those registers.
你知道，我经常混淆这两个，
And again, you know I I regularly confuse the two
可以回到这张表，看看它们是怎么用的。
and find myself returning to this table, to remind myself about what they do.
如果你记得读过的内容，
And so, You know you if you remember from the reading,
所有这些寄存器都是 64 位的，
all of these registers are 64 bits wide,
所以，它们有 64 个位置可以放东西，
so they have 64 places where we can put things
基于调用约定，各种类型数据适用于 64 位，
and the various data types are made to fit into those 64 bits based on the calling convention,
所以如果我们有一个 32 位整数，
so if we have a 32 bit integer,
根据它是不是扩展的，
depending on how it's whether or not it's an extended,
我们可以在它前面添加 0 或 1 ，
you know will either add zeros or ones to the front of that integer,
以便将其设置为 64 位放入这些寄存器。
in order to make it 64 bits to put in these registers.
在我们继续之前，
So before we move on,
有没有关于寄存器或相关的问题。
does anybody have questions about registers or things of that nature.
我有一个问题，
I have a question,
能把一个返回值放在 a1 中吗？
can you have a-, can you put a return value in a1.
是的，这是个好问题。
Yes, that's a good question.
我想理论上是可以的，
So, I think in theory you can,
原因是，比如 a0 到 a1 是，
the reason why we say a0 to a1 is
如果函数返回 128 位的长整型，
if a function returns a long long which is 128 bits,
如果你记得，如果一个函数参数是 100 ，超过一个指针字（pointer-word）长。
so if you remember from the reading if a function argument is a hundred is more than a pointer-word.
当我们说字（word）时，是 64 位，
We're , when we refer to word sign, we're saying 64 bits,
所以如果我们有两倍于指针字大小的东西，
so if we have something that is twice the size of a pointer-word,
我们可以把它放入寄存器对中，
we can put that in a register pair
因此同样的约定也适用于返回地址，
and so the same convention holds true for return addresses
如果我们有一个指针字两倍大小的东西，
where if we have something that's the size of twice pointer-word,
可以把它放在 a0 和 a1 中，并作为返回地址。
we can stick that in a0 and a1 and use that as the return address,
我想如果你只往 a1 里写入，可能会遇到问题。
I think you'll run into problems if you only try to put something in a1.
理解了，谢谢。
Makes sense, thanks.
为什么寄存器不是连续的，
Why are the registers not like continuous,
为什么 a0 和 a1 是分开的？
so why is like a0 and one separate from?
抱歉，这不是一个好例子，
Sorry no that's a bad example,
为什么 s1 和 s2 是分开的，
that's why is s1 separate from s2,
为什么 a 在它们中间，这有什么意义吗？
why the a in between like is there any point in that.
是的，我之前提到，
Yeah, so, I mentioned this briefly earlier,
这只是一个猜测，我不是很确定，
but there is a compressed, this is a guess I don't I don't know for sure,
有一个压缩版本的 RISC-V 指令，
but there's a compressed version of the RISC-V instructions
它的大小是 16 位，而不是 64 位。
which are 16 bits in size as opposed to 64.
你可以用它来使代码在内存中占用更少的空间，
And you would use that to try to make your code takes less space in memory,
当你使用 16 位指令时，只能访问寄存器 8 到 15 位，
and when you use those 16 bit instructions, you only have accesses to registers 8 through 15,
所以我认为 s1 与 s2 到 s11 分开，
so I think s1 is separate from s2 to eleven,
是因为他们想要明确，
because they want to make it clear,
s1 在压缩指令模式下可用，而 s2 到 s11 则不可用。
that s1 is available to you in the compressed instruction mode, whereas two to eleven aren't.
我不知道他们为什么选择 x ， x8 到 x15 ，
And the reason you know I don't know why they picked x, x8 to 15,
但我相信，只要看一些代码，
but I suspect that just looked at a bunch of code
就会发现这些是最常用的寄存器。
and we're like these are the most commonly used registers.
还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions?
我有一个问题。
I had a question .
除了帧指针、栈指针，
Besides the frame pointer, the stack pointer at all,
我不知道为什么我们需要更多的被调用者保存寄存器。
I don't know why we would need more callee saved registers.
但我们确实有很多这样的寄存器。
But we do have like a bunch of them.
是的， s1 到 s11 只是为了，
Yeah, the s1 to elevens those are just for,
我相信只是为了让编译器或程序员有使用它们的自由，
I believe use their freedom for the compiler or the programmer to use,
在某些情况下，你可能想要，
so there may be there are certain cases where you want,
想要保证在函数之后仍然有一些东西存在
you want to guarantee that something is still around after after your function,
可以调用编译器选择使用 s1 到 s11 来做。
call the compiler can choose to use s1 to eleven to do that.
嗯，我现在没有一个具体的例子来说明，
Um, I don't have like on hand, a specific example of where that's useful,
但是，我肯定它会出现的，
but, I'm sure it shows up,
where having a callee saved value is important.
这些基本上是程序员或编译器选择使用 s1 到 s11 。
But these are basically basically a programmer or compiler's choice to use s1 to eleven.
我要提醒一下，这些浮点寄存器，浮点算数，
I should note that these floating point registers their floating point, arithmetic,
据我所知，你们在这节课上不会看到它们，
as far as I'm aware, you won't see them in this class,
所以不需要担心它们。
and so you don't really need to worry about them.
好的，我们开始讨论一下函数调用，
Okay, so we started talking a little bit about function calls,
有了这些，我想开始讨论堆栈。
and so with that I want to move us into discussion of the stack .
这就是我们要讨论的堆栈，
So this is This is we're talking about the stack,
堆栈，就像你以前看到的那样，
and the stacked, if you've seen it like before,
它之所以重要是因为，
the reason why the stack is important is
它使函数保持组织和正常运行，
it's what keeps our functions organized and sane,
它允许函数工作，允许函数返回，
and it's what allows what makes functions work, it's what makes return work
这也是我们经常编写保存寄存器之类的代码。
and it's also where often we will find ourselves saving our registers and things like that.
嗯。
Um.
在这里，我给出了堆栈的一个非常简单的布局，
So, here, I've given just a pretty simple layout of what the stack looks like,
而且这里的每个框都是我们所说的栈帧。
and so each of these boxes here is what we refer to as a stack frame.
每次我们得到栈帧，都是由函数调用生成的。
And every time we get , which are generated by function calls.
每次我们调用一个函数，
Every time we call a function
该函数都会为自己创建栈帧，
that function makes for itself its own stack frame
并通过移动栈指针来使用它，
and which it uses itself and does that by moving around the stack pointer,
这个是栈指针，
so here's the stack pointer,
记住这些是很重要的。
and this is it's very important to remember.
对于栈，我们从高地址开始，然后向下扩展到低地址，
With stacks, we start from high addresses and we grow downwards. Too low addresses,
所以栈总是向下扩展。
so the stack grows down always.
所以你会看到栈指针的运算通常是通过减法来完成的，
And so you'll see that the arithmetic for stack pointer is usually done via subtraction,
我们要在汇编中创建一个新的栈帧，
we want to make a new stack frame in assemblies,
栈就向下扩展。
the stack grows downwards.
函数栈帧包含寄存器、局部变量，
And stack frames for function contain I see registers local variables,
就像我说的，
also like I was saying,
如果参数寄存器用完了，额外的参数就会出现在栈上，
if you run out of argument registers additional arguments will show up on the stack,
栈帧不一定是相同大小，
and so not as stack frames are not all the same size ,
尽管在这张图中它们是相同的，但事实并非如此，
even though they are in this diagram, that's not the case,
不同函数具有不同数量的局部变量，
different functions have different numbers of local variables
不同的寄存器等，
different registers so on and so forth,
因此栈帧具有不同的大小，
and so stack frames will be different sizes.
但是有两件事是可以确定的，
But the two things that you can definitely count on,
这很重要，返回地址总是在第一个，
which are important is that the return address will always be on the first thing
并且，帧指针，前一帧帧指针
and the frame pointer, the previous frames frame pointer
也会出现在栈中可预测位置，
is also going to show up on the stack at a predictable location,
两个重要的寄存器，这个是 sp ，
so the two important registers here are sp,
正如我们讨论的，这是栈的底部。
which you know as we discussed is used for, this is the bottom of the stack.
或者说是栈所在的位置，
Or generally you know it's the location of the stack,
fp 也是重要的寄存器，指向当前帧的顶部。
and then fp is are also important register and this points to the top of current frame.
这一点很重要，
And this is important,
因为这意味着返回地址和前一 fp
because that means that the return address and the previous fp
将始终位于当前帧指针的固定位置。
will always be at a fixed location from the current frame pointer.
这意味着如果我想找到返回地址，
So that means that if I want to find my return address
或者想找到上一帧，
or I want to find the previous frame,
我总是可以通过查看当前帧指针来获得这些值，
I can always get to those values by looking at the current frame pointer
我们之所以存储前一个帧指针，
and the reason why we store the previous frame pointer is
是为了可以向后跳转，
to allow us to jump back,
一旦这个函数返回，我们可以把它移动到 fp ，
so once this function returns we can move this into fp
然后，
and all of a sudden
fp 从指向这个栈帧，到指向这个栈帧。
fp again will go from pointing to this, this stack frame, to now pointing to this stack frame.
所以，我们使用帧指针来操作栈帧，
So we use the frame pointer to manipulate our stack frames
并确保始终指向函数对应的栈帧。
and make sure we're always going to one corresponding to the correct function.
这就是栈的工作方式，
And that's that's kind of how things how things are done
栈的这部分是使用汇编语言实现的，
and the these pieces of the stack need to be created by assembly
你读到的调用约定文档中的所有内容，
and so everything's everything in that calling conventions document that you read about
都是由编译器实施的，
that's all enforced by effectively by the compiler,
编译器遵循调用约定，生成栈帧，
so the compiler adheres to the calling convention and it's what generates the stack frame,
生成汇编代码，保证栈帧正确，
it generates the assembly code that makes our stack frames look correct,
所以通常在函数的开头，你会看到所谓的函数序言。
so often at the top of a function, you'll see what's called a function prologue.
然后是函数体，
And then there will be the body of the function
然后是一个函数尾声。
and then there will be an epilogue that shows up after that,
这就是汇编函数通常看起来的样子，
so this is kind of like, when an assembly function will often look like.
我们现在来看一下，
And we'll take a look at,
这里我有另一个函数 sum_then_double ，
now, so here I have another function sum_then_double,
注意， sum_to 没有这些东西，
so you'll note that [] that sum_to not have any of these things
一个真正的函数应该有的，
that it it should if it was a proper function
它也是可用的，因为足够简单，
and this works fine because it's simple enough,
它的所有计算都是在 a0 上进行的，
so it does all of its computations on a0
所以是好的，我们把它称为叶子函数，
and so things are, things are good and we're also not it's a it's a leaf function,
如果你看到叶子函数这个术语，
so, you'll see if you've seen the term leaf function
它是一个不调用另一个函数的函数，
that's a function that doesn't call another function,
这种函数的特殊之处是，
and the functions are special in that
它们不需要考虑保存自己的返回地址，
they don't need to worry about saving their own return address
或者保存任何调用者保存寄存器。
or saving really any of the caller saved registers.
因为它们不会进行另一个函数调用，
Because they're going to they're not going to make another function call,
所以它们不需要那么小心。
so they don't have to be as careful,
另一方面， sum_then_double 不是叶子函数，
sum_then_double on the other hand is not a leaf function,
你可以在这里看到，它调用了 sum_to 。
so you can see here, it calls sum_to.
所以它需要包含函数序言，
And so it does need to include that that prologue,
这里我们可以看到，从栈指针减去 16 ，
and so we see here that we are subtracting 16 from the stack pointer,
我们在栈上腾出空间，
so we're making space on our stack,
我们将 sum_then_double 的返回地址存储在栈中，
we're storing the return address for sum_then_double on the stack,
然后调用 sum_to ，
and then we make our call to sum_to,
在此之后，函数所做的全部工作就是调用 sum_to 。
and after that all this function does is it calls sum_to
然后将 sum_to 返回的结果加倍，
and then doubles the result, doubles the result turn by sum_to,
这里你可以看到函数尾声，
and here you can see the epilogue,
我们将返回地址加载回 ra ，
so we load the return address back in to ra
并删除栈帧，然后跳出函数。
and delete our stack frame and then jump out of the function.
我们可以运行它来确保达到预期的效果。
And so we can run that to make sure it does what we would expect.
在这里。
Go here.
我们可以运行，如果我们运行 demo1 ，
We can run, so if we run demo2 or demo1
我们得到了总和为 15 的结果，
we got the result of fifteen for the sum,
我会演示 demo2 ，调用 sum_then_double ，
and I'll tell you that demo2 just, just call sum_then_double
它就是把 sum_to 返回的结果加倍。
and indeed you know it happily doubles the sum returned by sum_to.
所以我有一个问题，
And so a question I have for anybody
如果我们删除这个函数序言和函数尾声，会发生什么，
what happens if we delete this prologue and epilogue,
如果我们在 sum_then_double 这样操作，会发生什么。
what happens if we just have this as our function, sum_then_double.
有人能预测会发生什么吗？
Can anybody predict what's going to happen.
我的意思是， sum_then_double 不知道它应该返回的返回地址，
I mean one thing is that sum_then_double wouldn't know the return address that it should return to,
因此，在调用 sum_to 时，将覆盖 sum_then_double 的返回地址，
so upon calling sum_to, that's going to override the return address to be sum_then_double's,
在 sum_then_double 的末尾，它不会返回到最初的调用者。
at the end of sum_then_double, it's not going to return to its original caller.
是的，没错。我们可以看看发生了什么。
Yeah exactly and we can see that that's what happens.
我们退出这个，退出这个，
Again, so if we exit out of this and exit out of this
我们现在用损坏的函数重新编译。
and we re-compile with now with our broken function.
我们可以看看到底会发生什么，
We can take a look at exactly what's gonna happen,
我们可以在 sum_then_double 设置中断，
so we can actually set our break point for sum_then_double.
设置 tui 并让它继续运行，
And set up tui and let it continue,
现在我们运行 demo2 ，
so we now run demo2,
好的，我们在 sum_then_double 。
okay we're at sum_then_double.
同样的，这里只有一个汇编函数，
And again, this is an assembly only function,
所以我们在汇编中查看它，
so we're going to want to look at it in assembly,
我们输入 layout asm ， layout reg ，
so we'll do layout asm layout reg,
因为这种情况下，寄存器的内容也很重要。
because it's important what's in the registers in this case.
你将看到 gdb 中有很多信息，
And you'll see that gdb knows a whole bunch of extra information
我们可以看到，
and so we can see that, you can see that,
ra 当前，返回地址指向 demo2 加 18 ，
ra currently, so the return address, currently points to demo2 the plus eighteen,
这表示进入函数 demo2 。
so, it points effectively into the function demo2.
现在我们可以运行，
And now we can run,
我们可以单步检查函数，看看会发生什么。
we can just kind of step through our function and see what happens.
我们调用了 sum_to ，
We've called sum_to
可以看到返回地址被 sum_to 覆盖，
and immediately we can see that the return address was overwritten by sum_to,
现在指向 sum_then_double 加 4 ，
to now point to sum_then_double plus four,
这是对的，就是我们期望的。
which makes sense, you know that's what we expect,
如果返回我们的代码，
if we go back into our code,
调用 sum_to ， sum_to 应该返回到这里。
we call sum_to and so sum_to should return to here.
现在我们可以单步，
And now we can step through you know so on up
然后我们再回到。
and then we get back into.
糟糕，出错了。
Oops, the wrong s.
好的，我们现在在这里，
Okay, so now we're here
当 sum_then_double 返回时，就像 Amir 说的，
and now when sum_then_double returns as exactly as Amir pointed out
它没有恢复自己的返回地址，
its return, it has not restored its own return address
而是它的返回地址仍然是 sum_to 使用的，
and instead its return address is still the one that was used by sum_to,
所以我们会进入一个无限循环，
and so we will get into an infinite loop
一遍又一遍地重复这个过程，
where we just keep doing this over and over and over again
永远不会结束。
and we'll never terminate from it.
我想这很好地说明了，
And so this is I think this is a good illustration of
为什么跟踪调用者保存和被调用者保存寄存器很重要，
why it's important to keep track of our caller versus callee saved registers
这也展示了
and hopefully this also shows
可以使用 gdb 来调试这类问题，
that you can use kind of gdb to debug these sorts of these sorts of problems,
让我们恢复之前的代码。
so let's restore what we had.
我将使用其他一些演示代码来讲解。
I will go into some other demos to talk about to illustrate .
有人问，我们为什么要减去 16 ？
Somebody ask why are we subtracting 16.
这是为了给栈帧腾出空间，
That's to put space to get our stack frame,
所以从栈指针中减去 16 ,
so this is subtracting 16 from the stack pointer,
它在内存中向下移动。
so it's moving it down basically in memory.
将其向下移动，以便我们有空间容纳自己的栈帧，
Moving it down so that we now have space for our own stack frame,
然后我们就可以把东西放在那里。
then we can stick stuff there.
因为这时候，我们不想覆盖栈指针上的东西，
So because at this point, in fact that we don't want to override what's at the stack pointer,
为什么不是 4 ，
why not 4 I is just well 4,
我们需要 16 ，因为指令是 64 位。
we need to do 16 because instructions are 64.
是的，我想实际上不一定需要 16 ，
Yeah I guess I guess we wouldn't don't actually need to do 16,
但通常你会看到，
but that's generally what you'll see generally just see,
我想不能使用 4 ，因为需要 8 ，
I don't think yeah you, you can't you can't do 4 because you need 8.
不能使用 4 ，但我想你可以使用指令大小，
So 4 doesn't work, but I think you could do the instruction size,
而寄存器大小是 64 位，
and the size of the register registers are 64,
那么为什么通常看到 16 是因为，
yeah, and then so the convention why you usually see 16 is because
如果我们回到文档，通常有返回地址和帧指针，
if we jump back to our document, usually we have the return address and the frame pointer ,
我们在这里不这样做，因为不是非常小心地处理我们的汇编。
we're not doing that here because or being [not super careful] with our assembly.
所以通常情况下，如果我们看内部，
So normally, if we if we look in,
我肯定，
I'm sure,
如果我们看内核，就会明白这一点。
if we look in kernel at this and we'll see.
我们查看内核数据，发现它也是 16 ，
Yeah, so we look in kernel data we see it's also 16,
这通常是编译器处理后看到的。
this is generally what you'll see with the compiler.
好的，现在我们可以。
Um, OK, so now we can.
在这之后。
After this.
我们修复函数，现在看一些 C 代码。
We fix our function and now we can look at some C code.
好的，现在我们有 demo4 ，
Alright, so here we have demo4
它基本上就是 main 函数的复制，
which is just basically, a copy of main function,
是对 main 函数的模拟，
like a imitation of the main function,
我们有 args ，它是一个字符串数组，
so we have our args, which is an array of strings
我们有 dummymain ，
and we have dummymain
它接收一些参数和参数字符串，
which takes a number of arguments and the arguments string
然后打印出来。
and just print it out, for us.
这就是所有的，都很简单，
And so that's all that's that's all that's happening here is pretty straightforward,
如果我们在 dummymain 中设置断点，
if we set a break point in dummymain,
然后跳过来。
then hop over, let.
好的，我们继续，运行 demo4 ，
Okay, we'll just continue and we start this run demo4,
现在我们到了 dummymain 。
okay so we now we hit dummymain.
有几件重要的事要记住，
And there's a couple of important things to remember about,
你可以使用 gdb 来显示栈帧，
that you can use gdb for regarding stack frames,
我们输入 i ，也就是 info ，
so if we type i so again, that's info,
如果我们输入 i frame ，可以看到很多关于当前栈帧的信息，
if we type i frame, we can see a whole bunch of useful information about the current stack frame,
可以看到，我们在栈级别 0 ，
so we can see we're at stack level zero,
级别 0 意味着它[]在调用栈下面，
level zero means it's [] is down in the call stack
我们可以转到，而且帧在这个地址。
that we can go and the frame is at this address.
程序计数器也没问题，一切都很好，
The program counter which is okay, that's all well and good,
我们有一个安全的程序计数器，
we have a safe program counter as well,
如果我们使用这个地址跳转到 kernel.asm 。
and if we again if we take this address and we jump into kernel.asm.
我们搜索那个地址，
We search for that address,
我们可以在 demo4 中找到那个地址，
we can indeed that that addresses inside of inside of demo4,
这正是我们希望程序返回的地址，
which is exactly where we expect the program to return to
它是由这个地址的帧调用的，
and it was called by a frame at this address
源代码 C ，
source language C,
很高兴知道这一点，
that's that's nice to know
然后我们有参数列表，也是从这个地址开始的，
and then we have the argument list also starts this address,
当然，本例中我们的大部分参数都在寄存器中，
of course, in this case, we have most of our arguments in registers
我们甚至可以看到 args 是什么，
and then we can even see what args are,
argc 是 3 ， argv 是这个地址。
we argc is three and argv is this address.
如果我们想要更深入研究一些东西，
And if we want a more in-depth examine things
可以使用 info args 命令，
we can look at things like info args,
它告诉我们有关函数参数的信息，我们可以查看，
which will tell us information about the arguments to the function, we can look at,
但更重要的是，我们可以输入 backtrace 或 bt ，
but more importantly we can type we type backtrace or bt works as well,
我们得到了整个栈帧的 backtrace ，
we get a full backtrace of all of the stacks,
调用栈中的所有栈帧，
all of the stack frames from the call stack,
你可以在这里看到一些问题，
so you can see something questionable happen here,
当我们调用系统调用时，
that's when we invoke a system call,
然后我们到达 usertrap 函数，
then we get to the usertrap function,
然后是 syscall 函数，
then to the syscall function,
然后是 sys_demo ，然后是 demo4 。
then to sys_demo then to demo4.
然后转到 dummymain ，
And then finally to dummymain
如果我们想更深入研究这些栈中的一个，
and if we want to investigate any of these stack frames more in-depth,
我们可以使用 frame 再加上一个数字，
we can do frame and then whatever number is along the side here,
比如我想看看当 syscall 调用时栈帧是什么，
so let's say I want to look at what was my stack frame when syscall called,
我可以查看第 3 帧，
I can go to frame three,
现在，在 gdb 里面，我正在查看栈帧，
and so now, inside of gdb, I'm looking at that stack frame,
我输入 info frame ，可以得到这个。
so I type info frame I can get this.
这里我们得到了更多信息，
And here we get a lot more a lot more information
有很多保存寄存器。
we have a bunch of saves registers.
我们有一些局部变量，
Um, we have some local variables,
这个函数没有任何参数，
we don't have any arguments to this function,
我们可看到程序计数器应该跳回到哪里，
we can see where the program counter were supposed to jump back to,
诸如此类的东西，
all kinds of things like that,
所以，如果你在调试东西，这是非常有用的。
so this is super super useful for if you're debugging things,
事实上，它非常有用，
and in fact it's so useful,
我们让你自己实现的版本，远不如 gdb 告诉你的那样深入。
we make you implement your own version, nowhere near as in depth as what gdb tells you,
我们在下一个实验中的练习之一，
but we're one of the exercises on the next lab
是实现你自己的 backtrace helper 函数，
will be to implement your own backtrace helper function,
以便在实验内调试时使用。
for use when debugging things inside the lab.
因此 backtrace 非常有用，
And so back backtrace is quite useful,
如果我们输入 frame 0 ，就会返回到刚才的位置。
and then if we type frame zero, we go back to where we were supposed to be.
如果我们想要调查，
And if we want to investigate,
你可能注意到这不是很有帮助，
you probably noticed it's not super helpful,
argv 是字符串数组形式的字符串，
you know argv is a string as an array of strings
而且我们只拿到了地址，
and so we just got a ref, we just get an address,
如果我们想看看地址里面是什么，
for where that's actually stored and if we want to look at what's in there,
有几种方法可以做到，
there's a couple ways of doing this,
最简单的是，输入 print ， p 表示打印，
the easiest is if we type print, p is for print,
然后我们间接引用该地址，
and then if we dereference the address,
我们看看地址那里是什么，
so we go look at what's at address,
我们这样做，
we do that and,
你知道，正如预期的，我们得到了该数组的第一个元素，
you know, as you would expect, we get the first element of that array,
因为当它试图打印字符串时，
because when it tries to print a string,
就像 C 语言里，它会一直运行，直到遇到空字符，
it'll go as C says, it'll go until it hits the null character,
所以我们得到 foo ，它是数组中的第一个元素，
so we get foo which is the first element in that array,
如果我们想要得到更多，可以加上一个长度，
and if we want to get more things we can put in the length,
如果我们输入 @ ，然后一个数字，
so if we do @ then a number,
它会上升到某个索引，
it'll go up to a certain index,
然后我们可以看到这两个字符串，
so then we can see both of the strings here
同样， gdb 非常聪明，
and again gdb is quite smart,
我们甚至可以用 argc 打印整个参数数组。
so we can even use argc to print out the whole argument array.
所有的信息对你来说都是可用的，
And so all of that information is available to you,
不管你想得到什么， gdb 是很有用的工具。
you , however you want to get it, so gdb the superpower tool.
为什么 gdb ，不好意思，
Why does gdb sorry,
为什么编译器有时候会优化 argc 和 argv ，
why does the compiler sometimes optimize out argc and argv,
之前发生过这样的事。
that has happened to be before.
这意味着编译器找到了一种更有效的方法，
Yeah that just means that the compiler found a more efficient way,
很可能只是去掉了变量，并进行所有操作，
likely it just got rid of the variable and it's doing all of its operations,
你知道[]寄存器可能在 a0 上执行所有操作，
directly you know [] register might be doing all of its operations on a0,
比如，它可能只是对返回地址进行所有计算。
for example, it might just be doing all the computations on the return address.
这很常见，
It's pretty common to see something like that,
如果它是一个非必须的变量。
if you if it's a variable that's not you know a hundred percent necessary.
我们不能控制编译器，
If you know we don't let we don't give you control over the compiler,
但是如果你在平时发现这个，
but if you ever find that in your day-to-day,
你可以尝试将编译器的优化标志设置为零，
you can try setting the optimization flag for the compiler to zero,
但即使这样，编译器仍会做一定程度的优化。
but even then you know the compiler will do will do it, we'll do some level of optimization.
Bibic 你举手了。
Bibic, your hand is raised.
是的，在 $1 和 $2 后面的地址是什么，就是在 foo 或 bar 之前的，
Yeah what's the address, besides that $1 or $2 you know like before foo or bar.
美元符号，你说这个吗？
Dollar, this?
是的，那个地址就是 foo 所在的地址。
Yeah, so what's that address is that the address where foo is.
可能是吧。
Probably yes.
但是，然后 argv 指向其他地址，它们不应该是相同的。
But then argv points to some other address shouldn't those be the same.
所以 argv 在这个栈上，
So argv is on this stack,
如果你看这些地址，
and you know, so the reason why, if you look at these addresses,
我们可以看到它们在内核中，就在 8000 。
we can see that they're in the kernel, just by the 8000.
这是有道理的，因为我们静态声明，
Um, which makes sense because we declared statically right,
所以在示例程序中，如果我走到这里，它们会在这里声明。
so in demos, if I go here they're declared here.
所以它们位于内核的某个地方，
And so they're basically they're sitting somewhere in the kernel
and they're all [] stars argc or argv is an array of [] stars
所以我想每个元素都指向自己的字符串，
and so I imagined each element points to points to its own string right,
它是一个指针数组。
so it's an array of pointers.
我明白了。
I see.
[]
我也有一个问题，
I also have a question about this,
$3 版本的数组具有，
the $3 version of the array has
如果看这些地址，
if I look at these addresses
第一个后缀是 38 ，
the first one is suffixed by 38,
第二个后缀是 40 ，
the second one is suffixed by 40
第三个是 48 。
and the third one is 48.
这不是统一的，虽然三个参数的长度都是三个，
Which is not uniform, even though the length of each of the three arguments is three,
所以为什么它们是不同的。
so why, why are they different.
嗯，我也不是百分百确定，
Um, not in I'm not a hundred percent certain,
我猜是为了对齐数据。
my guess is that this is an attempt to align things.
让它们保持合理的位置，
Um, right, so to get them on a reasonable alignment,
有人指出它们用十六进制表示是对齐的。
it is uniform in hex as, people are pointing out.
好的，理解了，谢谢。
Oh yeah, yeah yeah see it now right, thanks.
所以有时候你看到东西放在那里很奇怪，
So you'll sometimes see where strange things are laid out strangely
可能是两个东西有不同的偏移量，
where there might be two things as strange offsets
因为并不是所有的东西都是相同大小的。
and that's just because not everything is naturally the same sized.
好的，还有其他问题吗？
Okay, any other questions.
好的，我们可以跳过第五个 demo 。
Okay, we can skip the fifth demo.
gdb 的另一个有用的功能是，
And so another useful function that we get from gdb,
不仅有断点，还有观察点，
instead of just break points, they're also watch points
并且我们还可以设置有条件的断点。
and we can also set a conditional break points.
我简单介绍一下。
So, I'll just briefly go over that.
运行 demo6 以便我们可以在函数中设置，
Run demo6 so we can set inside this function,
我们可以设置观察点，
we can watch so we can set a watch point,
我想在这里你可以看到。
I think here you'll see .
向 Luke 所说的，一些东西被优化了，
Yeah, so here you'll see what Luke was talking about where we see that some has been optimized out,
可能是因为它只是零或别的什么。
likely because it's just being a zero or something.
我们可以看一下这个汇编，
We can look even at the assembly for this right,
我们可以使用 layout split 。
so we can layout split.
事实上，可以看到所有都是在栈上完成的，
And indeed, we can see that all just being, It's all just being done on the stack,
在我看来。
it looks like to me.
不，这都是在 s0, s0 1 3 上做的，
Oh, no, it's always been done in s0 s0 one three,
在这里你可以看到，编译器使用的是被调用者保存寄存器，
so here you can see the, compiler decided even to use the callee saved registers
这样我们可以设置，对 i 进行观察。
and so we can set things like we do watch on i.
好的，我们还没有声明 i ，
Alright we haven't declared i,
因为我们不在循环里面，
yet because we're not inside we're not inside the for loop.
所以我们单步执行 C 代码，
So we step through the C instructions,
现在我们对本地变量查看信息，会看到 i ，
now if we do information for the locals, we see we get i,
我们甚至可以在 sum 设置观察点。
we can even watch watch point on sum.
现在任何时候 sum 改变都会收到通知，
So now anytime that sum changes will actually get a notification,
我们继续，然后这里有一个删除，
so we can continue and then we'll get a delete here,
因为有东西被删除了，所以我们不能查看它，
because some has been moved so we can't we can't actually watch it,
我们甚至可以做一些事情，比如在 sum_to 上设置断点，
we can even do things like break point on sum_to,
这是一个条件断点，如果 i 现在是 1 ，
so this is a conditional break point if, well, let's actually see was i currently, so i currently 1,
比如，让循环在 i 是 5 的时候中断，
let's say I think my loop is breaking and whenever i is 5,
如果我想专门调试这种情况，
well if I want to specifically debug that case,
我可以在 sum_to 上设置一个断点，如果 i 等于 5 。
I can set a break point on sum_to if i equal 5.
现在我们有了这个断点，如果我们继续
So now we have this break point, and if we continue along,
我们得到 sum_to ，可以看到它打印了第一组值，
we'll get to sum_to, and we can see that it actually printed out the first couple values
现在我们只在 i 符合条件时在 sum_to 上中断。
and so we only break now on sum_to if if i if we hit that break point condition.
也就是说，如果你要调试代码特定的边界条件，它会很有用，
And so that's, it can be again can be useful if you want to debug specific edge cases of your code
观察点可能会很有用，
and watch points can be useful
如果你认为某些东西不应该改变，但你怀疑它改变了，
if for instance you think that something shouldn't be changing, but you suspect that it is
或者你认为每次你改变某个变量都会出问题。
or you think that something is going wrong every time you change a certain variable.
这是它的一种用法。
And so that's that's a it's one one usage for that.
今天，我最后要说的是结构体（struct），
And the last thing I want to talk about today is struct,
结构体非常重要，它会经常出现在实验里，
struct pretty important, they'll come up in in the labs often
还有。
and also.
所以我会简单介绍一下结构体在内存中的布局。
So, what as, I'll talk a little bit about the way structs are laid out in memory.
基本上，一个结构体就是一个连续的内存区域，
And so a structure is basically it's a continued contiguous area of memory,
所以如果我们有一些结构体。
so if we have some structure.
我们有字段一，字段二，字段三。
And we have like field one field two field three.
当我们创建该结构体时，
When we make that struct
在内存中，这些字段将挨着排在一起。
those fields are going to be align next to each other in memory,
你可以把它想象成一个数组，
you can kind of think of this like an array,
但是 f1 f2 f3 可以是不同的类型。
but f1 f2 f3 can all be different types.
而且，我们可以把它们传递给函数，
And, we can pass them [] functions,
它们作为参数传递给函数，通常是通过引用，
usually they pass them as arguments to functions, usually they pass by reference,
这里有一个结构体 person ，包含两个整型参数，
so here I've made a struct person with two integer arguments,
我传递一个 person 作为参数，
and I'm passing them, passing a person as an argument person
并打印出其中的一些信息，
and printing out some of that information,
如果我们进入 gdb ，
so if we hop into gdb
让我们删除所有的断点和观察点，
and let's delete all our break points and watch points,
现在我们在 printPerson 上设置一个断点，
and now we can set a break point at printPerson,
继续，并运行第七个 demo 。
and it's continue and run seventh demo.
现在可以看到，我们在这里，如果输入 i frame ，
We can see that now we're here and so if we type i frame,
我们可以看到，我们有一个参数 p 。
we can see that we have an argument p.
事实上，如果我们打印 p ，
And indeed, we can see if we do print p,
甚至能辨别出这个地址是 struct person ，
If we can even tell that it's struct person at this address
我们可以间接引用它，
and we can if we dereference it,
gdb 告诉我们 p 的 id 是 1215 ， age 是 22 。
gdb will tell us exactly what p looks like it has id 1215 age 22.
只是展示一下结构提是怎么存放的。
And just to show kind of how things are laid out.
你可以取这个地址，我们可以在这个地址看到，
You can take this address and we see at this address,
如果我们看。我记得很清楚。
if we look. I remember exactly.
应该是的。
Should be.
如果我们再来一次，可以用这个来调试我们的结构体。
So if we again so we can use this to debug our structures.
在代码中，我们可以看一下结构体是怎么回事，
In in the code, we can take a look at what's going on with structures this way,
因此 gdb 是非常强大的工具，
so gdb is a super powerful tool
不仅用于单步执行，
not just for stepping through code,
还用于检查代码中各种类型的潜在问题。
but also for examining all kinds of potentially problematic pieces in your code
而且可以查看参数和栈帧，
and looking at arguments and stack frames and things like that,
这在下一个实验中很有用，
and this will be hopefully will be useful in the next lab,
当你必须使用栈帧和汇编来编程时。
when you have to work with, with stack frames and with assembly code.
这就是我今天想讲的主要内容。
So that's that's mostly what I wanted to talk about today.
最后还有 7 分钟，
So, with the last kind of seven minutes of lecture,
你们可以提任何问题。
I'll open it up to any any other questions you guys have.
我有一个离题的问题，
I had a bit of a tangential question,
谁管理从 C 到各种指令集架构
who is who manages the creation of compilers
的编译器的创建，
from to get from C to various instruction set architectures,
是指令集架构的创建者，或是类似的但三方机构。
is that the creator of the instruction set architecture, is the third parties like that.
我想不是指令集的创建者，
Um, I believe that it is not the creative the instruction set,
通常是第三方，
so it's often a third party,
你们知道的的两个大的 C 编译器，
so the two big C compilers that you'll see
GCC 是由 GNU 基金会维护的，
refer to GCC which is maintained by I think the GNU foundation
Clang llvm 是自己维护的，
and Clang llvm, which is its own thing,
你可以发现， llvm 甚至是开源的，
so I think you know you can find I believe llvm is even open source,
这样你就能找到，专门做这件事的代码。
so you can find. you can, you can find the code specifically that does this,
当一个像 RISC-V 的新指令集发布时，
when a new instruction set is released such as RISC-V,
调用约定文档以及所有这些指令文档一起发布，
that calling convention document as well as all of those instruction documents,
我猜，
I think carefully I assume
可能编译器设计者和指令集设计者之间有高级别的合作。
there's a high level of cooperation between the compiler designer and the instruction set designer .
但简单来说，我相信是第三方维护的，
But yeah a short answer is I believe it's a third party who does it,
很可能与指令集制作人员的大量合作。
likely with a lot of cooperation from the people who make the instruction set.
RISC-V 可能是一个例外，因为它来自一个研究项目，
RISC-V is probably, RISC-V might be an exception where because it came out of a research project,
他们可能也自己编写了编译器。
they may have written the compiler for it themselves, as well.
我不认为英特尔在 GCC 或 llvm 上有所投入。
I I don't think Intel has for example has input in in GCC or llvm.
还有其他问题吗？
Other questions?
好的，感谢收听，
Okay, well, thanks for listening,
那样的话，我想我们可以。
in that case I guess we can.
你可以在这里结束，
You can end the lecture here,
还有 5 分钟，好好休息一下。
a five minutes to spare, so have a nice rest.